<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Charles, by the grace of God, King of Scotland, England, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Fayth, to our lovits  ...</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1638-11-29</title>
            <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15699</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843239</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176900</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240915565</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 21999.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S107540</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99843239e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 717:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Charles, by the grace of God, King of Scotland, England, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Fayth, to our lovits  ...</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1638-11-29</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Hamilton, James Hamilton, Duke of, 1606-1649. Declaration on episcopal government in Scotland. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28, 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Raban, according to the true copie imprinted at Edinburgh, by Robert Young, printer to the King's most excellent Majestie. Cum Privilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon (A1r).</note>
                  <note>A proclamation dissolving the General Assembly, 29 Nov., 1638.</note>
                  <note>Includes also Hamilton's declaration on episcopal government against acknowledging the Glasgow Assembly.</note>
                  <note>Text begins A2r.</note>
                  <note>With continuous signatures.</note>
                  <note>First proclamation occupies A2r-C1v. C2r-H1v consist of James Hamilton's declaration on episcopal government in Scotland (also issued separately as STC 12728). H2r-M1v consist of another proclamation by Charles I made against acknowledging the Glasgow Assembly on Dec. 8, 1638 (also issued separately as STC 22000).--Folger Shakespeare Library catalog.</note>
                  <note>Not in Steele.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21999a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Proclamations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176900:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ABERDENE,</hi> Printed by Edward Raban, According to the true Copie Imprinted at Edinburgh, by Robert Young, Printer to the King's most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majestie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CƲM PRIVILEGIO.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:176900:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Insignia Vrbis abredonie;</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:176900:2"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES, By the Grace of GOD, King of SCOTLAND, ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND, FRANCE, and IRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND, Defender of the Fayth, To Our Lovits,</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>Heraulds, Pursevaunts; Our Shyreffs in that part conjunctlie and severallie, specially constitute, Greeting. Forsameikle as out of the Royall and Fatherly Care which We haue had of the Good and Peace of this Our Ancient &amp; Natiue Kingdome; having taken to Our serious Consideration, all such things as might haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Contentment to Our good and loyall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: And to this ende had discharged, by Our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176900:3"/>Proclamation, the Service Booke, Booke of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and High Commission, Freed and liberate all men from the practising of the fiue Articles, Made all Our Subjects, both Ecclesiasticall &amp; Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, lyable to the Censure of Parliament, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Assemblie, or anie other judicatorie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, according to the nature and qualitie of the Offence: And for the free entire of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, That no other Oath bee administrate vnto them, than that which is contayned in the Act of Parliament: Had declared all by gone Disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, absolutelie forgotten, and forgiven: And for the more full &amp; cleare extirpating all ground and occasion of Fears of innovation of Religion, Wee had commanded the Confession of Fayth, and Band for Mayntenance thereof, and of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in defence of the same, subscrybed by Our deare Father, and His House-holde, in ANNO 1580, to be renewed, and subscrybed agayne by our Subjects here: Lyke as for setling of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Peace in the Church and Common-wealth of this Kingdome, We caused indict a Free Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assemblie, to bee holden at Glasgow, the xxj of this instant, and thereafter a Parliament in May, 1639. By which clement Dealing, Wee looked assuredlie, to haue reduced Our Subjects, to their former quyet behaviour, &amp; duetifull car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, whereto they are bound by the Word of GOD, and Laws both Nationall and Municipall, to Us their Natiue and Soveraygne Prince. And albeit the wished Effects did not follow, but by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176900:3"/>the contrarie, by Our so Gracious procedure, they were rather emboldened, not onlie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their stubborne and vnlawfull wayes; but also daylie adde to their former procedures, acts of neglect, and contempt of Authoritie; as evidentlie appeared by open opposing of Our just and religious Pleasure, and Command, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest in Our last Proclamation, anent the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the Service Booke, Booke of Canons, High Commission, &amp;c. protesting agaynst the same, and stryving by manie indirect means, to withdraw the hearts of Our good People, not onlie from an heartie acknowledgement of Our gracious dealing with them; but also from the due obedience to those Our just and religious Commands, notwithstanding We had bene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlie so often petitioned by themselues for the same: By their daylie and hourlie guarding and watching about Our Castle of Edinburgh, suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nothing to be imported therein, but at their discretion: And openlie stopping, and impeding, anie importation of Ammunition, or other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries whatsoever to anie other of our Houses, within that Kingdome: Denying to vs their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraygne Lord, that Libertie and Freedome, which the meanest of them assume to themselues, (an Act without Precedent or example in the Christian world:) By making of Convocations, and Councell Tables of Nobilitie, Gentrie, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and Ministers, within the Citie of Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh: Where, not regarding the Lawes of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176900:4"/>Kingdome, they without warrand of Authoritie conveane, assemble, and treat vpon Matters, as well Ecclesiasticall as Civil, send their injunctions and directions throughout the Countrey, to their subordinate Tables, and other vnder Ministers, appoynted by them for that effect. And vnder colour and pretext of Religion, exercing an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warranded and vnbounded libertie, require obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their illegall and vnlawfull procedures and directions, to the great and seene prejudice of Authoritie, and lawfull Monarchicall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And notwithstanding it was evidentlie manifest, by the illegall and vnformall course, taken in the election of their Commissioners for the Assemblie, whereof some are vnder the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of this Church, some vnder the censure of the Church of Ireland, and some long since bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, for open and avowed teaching agaynst Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie; others of them suspended, and some ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Ministerie, contrarie to the forme prescrybed by the Laws of this Kingdome; others of them a long time since denounced Rebels, and put to the Horne, who by all law and vnviolable custome and practique of this Kingdome, are, and ever haue beene, incapable, eyther to persue, or defende before anie judicatorie; farre lesse to bee judges themselues: some of them confined, and all of them by oath and subscription, bound to the overthrow of Episcopacie. And by this, and other their vnder-hand working, and private informations, and perswasions, haue given just
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176900:4"/>ground of suspicion of their partialitie herein, and so made themselues vnfit judges of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth Episcopacie. And als it was sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie cleared by the peremptorie and illegall proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures of the Presbyteries, who at their owne hand by order of Law, and without due forme of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, thrust out the Moderators lawfullie esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished, &amp; placed others, whom they found most inclinable to their turbulent humours, associate to themselues, for the choosing of the sayd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners for the Assemblie, a laicke Elder out of each Paroch, who being in most places equall, if not moe in number than the Ministerie, made choyce both of the Ministers, who should bee Commissioners from the Presbyteries, as also of a ruling Elder, beeing directed more therein by the warrands from the fore-sayde pretended Tables, than by their owne judgementes, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the severall private instructions sent from them, farre contrarie to the Lawes of the Countrey, and lowable custome of the Church: by which doinges it is too manifest, that no calme nor peaceable procedure or course, could haue beene expected from this Assemblie, for setling of the present disorders and distractions. Yet wee were pleased heerein, in some sort, to blinde-folde our owne judgement, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looke the sayds disorders, and patientlie to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende the meeting of the sayde Assemblie: still hoping, that when they were met together, by Our Commissioner his presence, and assistance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176900:5"/>of such other well-disposod subjects who were to hee there, and by their owne seeing the reall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of all that was promised by our last Proclamation, they should haue beene induced to returne to their due obedience of Subjectes: But perceaving that their seditions disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion still increaseth, by their repairing to the sayde Assemblie, with great Bands and Troupes of Men, all boddin in feare of Warre, with Gunnes and Pistolers, contrarie to the Lawes of this Kingdome, custome observed in all Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and in high contempt of our last Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Edinburgh the xvj of this instant: As also by their peremptory refusing of our assessors au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by vs, (altho fewer in number, than our dearest Father was in vse to haue at divers Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies) the power of voting in this assembly, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlie they haue done in other Assemblies; &amp; by their partiall, vnjust, and vnchristian refusing, and not suffering to bee read, the Reasons and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments given in by the Bishops, and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, to Our Commissioner, why the Assemblie ought not to proceede to the Election of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator without them, neyther yet to the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of anie of the Commissioners, of the saydes Commissioners from Presbyteries, before they were heard object agaynst the same, though ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestlie requyred by Our Commissioner in Our Name. And notwithstanding that Our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner vnder his hand, by warrand from Us, gaue in a sufficient declaration, of all that was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176900:5"/>contayned in Our late Proclamation and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the same bearing lykewyse Our pleasure, of the Registration of the same in the Bookes of Assemblie, for the full assurance of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to all our good subjects: And yet not resting satisfied therewith, lest the continuance of their meeting together, might produce other the lyke dangerous Acts, derogatorie to Royall Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Wee haue thought good, for preveening thereof, and for the whole causes and reasons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned, and diverse others, importing the true Monarchicall government of this estate, to dissolue and breake vp the sayde Assemblie. And therefore</p>
            <p>OUR WILL IS, and Wee doe dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge and inhibite all and whatsoever pretended Commissioners, and other members of the sayd pretended Assemblie, of all further meeting and conveaning, treating and concluding anie thing belonging to the sayd As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblie, vnder the payne of Treason: declaring all and whatsoever that they shall happen to doe in anie pretended meeting thereafter, to bee null, of no strength, force, nor effect, with all that may follow therevpon: Prohibiting and discharging all our Lieges to giue obedience thereto, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring them, and everie one of them, free and exempt from the same, and of all hazard that may ensue for not obeying thereof. And for this effect We command and charge, all the foresayds
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176900:6"/>pretended Commissioners, and other members of the sayde Assemblie, to depart foorth of this Citie of Glasgow; within the space of xxiv houres after the publication heereof, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire home to their own houses, or that they goe about their owne private affaires in a quyet man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. With speciall provision alwayes, that the foresayd Declaration, given in vnder our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners hand, with all therein contained, shall notwithstanding hereof, stand full, firme, and sure, to all Our good Subjects, in all tymes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, for the full assurance to them of the true Religion. And Our Will is, and Wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and charge, That incontinent, these Our Letters seene, yee passe, and make publication hereof, by open proclamation, at the market crosse of Glasgow, and other places needfull, where-through none pretend ignorance of the same.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given vnder our Signet, at Glasgow, <date>the xxix of November, and of Our Reygne the fourteenth yeare, 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
               <hi>Sic subscribitur,</hi>
               <signed>HAMMILTOUN, Traquaire, Roxburgh, Murray, Linlithgow, Perth, Kingorne, Tullibardin, Hadington; Galloway, Annandaill, Lauderdaill, Kinnoull, Dumfreis, Southesk, Belheaven, Angus, Dalyell, I. Hay, W. Elphingstone, Ia. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>michaell, I. Hammiltoun.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:176900:6"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here-as some haue given out, That by the Act of Coūcel, which explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Confession of Faith latelie commaunded to bee sworne by his Majestie, to be vnderstood of the Confession of Fayth, as it was then professed and receaved, when it was made; and, that in that Confession defence both of the Doctrine &amp; Discipline then established, is sworne; at which tyme, Episcopall Government being (as they say) abolished; it must needs follow, that the same Government is by this late Oath abjured.</p>
            <p>And vnderstanding that even amongst those who continue together still at Glasgow, vnder the name of a pretended and vnlawfull Generall Assemblie, this objection is helde to bee of some moment, and vsed by them, to the great distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the peace of this Church &amp; Kingdome, &amp; to the great disquyeting of the mynds of such his Majesties good subjectes, as haue taken the said Oath, &amp; yet never meaned, nor doe meane, to abjure Episcopall Government; And to perswade others, that if they shall take the same Oath, thus
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176900:7"/>explayned by the sayd Act of Councell, by so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they must likewise abjure the said governmēt.</p>
            <p>We IAMES Marques of Hamilton, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties high Cōmissioner, wondring that any such scrupulous misconstruction should bee made of his Majesties gracious and pious intentions; and beeing desirous to remoue all doubtes from the mynds of his Majesties good subjects, &amp; to keepe them from being poysoned by such as by forced and forged inferences, would make them belieue, that they had actuallie, by taking that Oath, sworne that which neyther virtuallie nor verilie they haue sworne, or ever intended to sweare, or was required by Authoritie to bee sworne by them, eyther directlie or indirectlie: Considering that all Oaths must be taken accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the mynd, intention, and cōmandement of that Authoritie which exacteth the Oath: and, that we, by speciall commandement from his sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majestie, commanded the sayde Oath to bee administred, we doe hereby freely &amp; ingenuously professe and declare our mynd &amp; meaning herein, as we haue constantlie heretofore done since our comming into this Kingdome about this imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>viz.</hi> That by anie such wordes, or Act of Councell, we never meaned or intended that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scopall Government should be abjured, nor anie thing else which was established by Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or Acts of the Church of this kingdome, which are now in force, and were so at the tyme of the taking of the sayd Oath.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:176900:7"/>
            <p> Nor indeed could we haue any other intention or meaning, being clearlie warranded, &amp; express<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie commaunded by his Majesties instructions, to exact the sayd Oath, and take order, that it should be sworn throughout the Kingdome, in that faire and lawfull sense, and none other.</p>
            <p>Neyther in this poynt did wee deliver our own words, or his Majesties mynd, ambiguouslie, or doubtfullie, so as anie other sense, to our thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, could be picked or wrung out of eyther the one or the other: For we doe attest the Lords of the Councell, whether we did not to manie, or all of them, vpon severall occasions, in conference with them, ever since our comming into this Kingdome, constantlie declare vnto them, that his Majesties resolution was not to suffer Episcopall Government to be abolished: Wee attest all the Lordes of Session, whether before our tendering of that Oath to them, or their Lordships taking of it, wee did not fullie and freelie declare to them, that his Majesties mynd, in commanding vs to see this Oath taken, and our owne mynd in requiring them to take it, was onlie to settle, and secure the Religion and Fayth professed in this Kingdome; but was not to bee extended to the abjuring of Episcopall Government, or anie other thing now in force, by the Lawes of this Church and State, at the time of administring this Oath; which their Lordships, being the Reverend and Learned Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Laws, knew well could not be abjured: after which perspicuous predeclaration of our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176900:8"/>mynd, their Lordships vndoubtedlie in that same sense, and none other, tooke the sayd Oath.</p>
            <p>And now, good Reader, having heard his Majesties mynd and intention, and in pursuance of them, the mynd of his Majesties high Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioner concerning this Oath, the reasons to repell the former objection, seeme to be needlesse, (the knowne mynde of the supreme Magistrate, who vrgeth an oath, being to be taken for the vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted sense of it:) yet forasmuch as that objection hath of late beene maynlie vrged, for alienating the myndes of manie of his Majesties good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and well-affected to that Government, from adhering vnto it, bee pleased to knowe, That the former objection hath neyther showe nor force of reason in it; and, That by the sayd Oath, and that explanation set downe in the Act of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, Episcopall Government neyther was, nor possiblie could bee abjured; and that for manie reasons, but especiallie these fiue, which wee ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving seene and approved, haue caused to bee here inserted, and leaue them to thyne impartiall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration.</p>
            <p>First:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> GOD forbid it should be imagined, that his Majesty should command his Subjects to take an Oath, which in it selfe is absolutelie vnlawful. But for a man to sweare agaynst a thing which is established by the Lawes of Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in which he liveth, (vnlesse that thing be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Law of GOD) is absolutelie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, vntill such tyme as that Kingdome and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176900:8"/>Church doe first repeale those Laws: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Episcopall Government not being repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Law of GOD, nay, being consonant vnto it, as beeing of Apostolicall Institution, (which shall be demonstrated, if anie man please to argue it) and standing fullie established, both by Acts of Parliament, and Acts of Generall As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblie, at the tyme when this Oath was admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred; to abjure it before those Acts bee repealed, is absolutelie vnlawfull, and agaynst the Word of GOD: and it is to be hoped, no man will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that his Majestie meaned to commaund a thing absolutelie vnlawfull. And if it should be sayd, as it is sayde by some, (who not being able to avoyde the force of Reason, doe betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to pittifull shifts, and evasions) that those Acts of Parliament and Assemblie, establishing Episcopall Government, were vnlawfullie and vnduelie obtayned: certaynlie, if they haue anie reasons for this their bold assertion, which is of a more dangerous consequence, than that it ought to be endured in any well setled Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, these reasons may bee presented lawfullie to these judicatories, to entreat them to reduce the saydes Acts, if there shall bee strength and vadilitie found in them. But to holde, that vntill such time as these judicatories shall repeale the saydes Lawes, they eyther ought to bee, or can possiblie bee abjured, is a wicked position, and destructiue of the verie foundation of justice, both in Church and Common-wealth.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:176900:9"/>
            <p> Secondlie,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it can not bee imagined that this Oath should oblige the now takers of it, farther than it did oblige the takers of it at first: for Doctrine and poynts of Fayth it did oblige them then, and so doeth it vs now, perpetuallie, because these poynts in themselues are perpetuall, immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and eternall: But for poynts of Discipline and Government, and Policie of the Church, that Oath could binde the first takers of it no longer than that Discipline and Government should stand in force by the Laws of this Church and Kingdome, which our Church in her posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Confession of Fayth, printed amongst the Actes of Parliament, Article 20.21. declareth to bee alterable at the will of the Church it selfe, and so repealable by succeeding Actes, if the Church shall see cause. When a King at his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation taketh an Oath to rule according to the Lawes of this Kingdome, or a Iudge at his admis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion sweareth to giue judgement according to these Lawes, the meaning of their Oathes can not bee that they shall rule or judge according to them, longer than they continue to be lawes: But if anie of them shall come afterwardes to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie repealed, both King &amp; Iudge are free from ruling and judging, according to such of them as are thus lawfully repealed, notwithstanding their originall Oath. Since therefore, if the first takers of that Oath were nowe aliue, they could not bee sayde to haue abjured Episcopall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which hath beene since established by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176900:9"/>Lawes of this Church and Kingdome, especiallie cōsidering that this Church in her confession hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, Church Government to bee alterable at the will of the Church: certaynlie wee repeating but their Oath, can not bee sayde to abjure that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment now, more than they could bee sayde to doe it, if they were now aliue, and repeating the same Oath.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie: How can it be thought,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that the verie act of his Majesties cōmanding this oath, should make Episcopall Government to bee abjured by it, more than the <hi>Covenanters</hi> requiring it of their associates, in both <hi>Covenants</hi> the wordes and syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labes of the <hi>Confession of Fayth</hi> being the same? Now, it is well known, that manie were brought in, to subscribe their <hi>Covenant,</hi> by the solemne protestations of the <hi>Contrivers</hi> and <hi>Vrgers</hi> of it, that they might subscribe it without abjuring of <hi>Episcopacie,</hi> and other such thinges as were esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by <hi>Lawe,</hi> since the tyme that this <hi>Oath</hi> was first invented and made: and the three Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, in their first <hi>Answeres</hi> to the <hi>Aberdene Quaeres,</hi> haue fullie and clearlie expressed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to that sense; holding these thinges for the present, not to bee abjured, but onlie referred to the tryall of a <hi>Free Generall Assemblie:</hi> and lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse the <hi>Adherers</hi> to the last <hi>Protestation,</hi> agaynst his Majesties <hi>Proclamation,</hi> bearing date the 9 of <hi>September,</hi> in their ninth <hi>Reason,</hi> agaynst the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription</hi> vrged by his Majestie, doe playnlie averre, <hi>That this Oath vrged by his Majestie,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176900:10"/>doeth obliedge the takers of it, To mayntayne Pearth Articles; and, To mayntayne Episcopacie.</hi> Why, therefore, some men swearing the same wordes and syllabes, should haue their wordes taken to another sense, and bee thought to abjure <hi>Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Governament,</hi> more than others who haue taken the same <hi>Oath</hi> in the same wordes, must needes passe the capacitie of an ordinarie vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</p>
            <p>It is a receaved Maxime,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and <hi>it can not bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, but that Oathes ministred vnto vs, must eyther bee refused, or else taken according to the knowne mynde, professed intention, and expresse Command of Authoritie, vrging the same.</hi> A <hi>Proposition,</hi> not onlie receaved in all Schools, but positiuelie set downe by the <hi>Adherers</hi> to the sayde <hi>Protesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, totidem verbis,</hi> in the place aboue cited. But it is notoriouslie knowne, even vnto those who subscribed the <hi>Confession of Fayth,</hi> by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties commandement, that his Majestie not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in his Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> is a <hi>Mayntayner</hi> and <hi>Vp-holder</hi> of <hi>Episcopall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> according to the Lawes of the sayde Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Kingdomes; but that lykewyse hee is a <hi>Defender,</hi> and intendeth to continue a <hi>Defender</hi> of the same <hi>Government</hi> in his Kingdome of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> both before the tyme, and at the tyme when hee vrged this <hi>Oath;</hi> as is evident by that which is in my Lord Commissioner his <hi>Preface,</hi> both concerning his Majesties <hi>Instructions</hi> to his Grace, and his Graces expressing his Majesties
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176900:10"/>mynde, both to the Lordes of <hi>Councell,</hi> and to the Lordes of <hi>Session.</hi> And the same lykewyse is playnlie expressed and acknowledged by the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herers</hi> to the sayde <hi>Protestation,</hi> in the place aboue cited; their wordes beeing these, <hi>And it is most manifest, that his Majesties mynde, intention, and commaundement, is none other, but that the Confession bee sworne, for the mayntenance of Religion, as it is alreadie or presentlie professed; (these two beeing co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incident altogether one and the same, not onelie in our common forme of speaking, but in all his Majesties Proclamations:) and thus as it concludeth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth within the compasse thereof, the foresaydes Novations and Episcopacie, which vnder that name were also ratified, in the first Parliament holden by his Majestie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence it is playne, that <hi>Episcopacie</hi> not beeing taken away, or suspended by anie of his Majesties <hi>Declarations,</hi> as those other things were which they call <hi>Novations,</hi> it must needes, both in deede, and in the judgement of the sayde <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> no wayes bee intended by his Majestie, to bee abjured by the sayd <hi>Oath.</hi> Nowe, both the <hi>Major,</hi> and that part of the <hi>Minor,</hi> which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Episcopall Government</hi> in the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> beeing clearlie acknowledged by the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters;</hi> and the other part of the <hi>Minor,</hi> concerning that <hi>Government</hi> in his other two Kingdomes, beeing notoriouslie knowne, not onlie to them, but to all others, who knowe his Majestie, how it can bee imagined, that his Majestie, by that <hi>Oath,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:176900:11"/>should command <hi>Episcopacie</hi> to bee abjured; or howe could anie one, to whome his Majesties mynde, concerning <hi>Episcopall Government,</hi> was knowne, honestlie or safelie abjure it, let it be left to the whole world to judge; especiallie conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the <hi>Protesters</hi> themselues in that place aboue cited, by a <hi>Dilemma,</hi> which wee leaue to themselues to answere, haue averred, that when that <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Councell</hi> should come out; yet that it could not be inferred from thence, that anie such thing was abjured.</p>
            <p>Fiftlie and lastlie;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> if the <hi>Explanation</hi> in that <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Councell</hi> bee taken in that not onlie rigid, but vnreasonable and senselesse sense which they vrge, yet they can never make it appeare, that <hi>Episcopall Government</hi> at the first time of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministring of that <hi>Oath</hi> was abolished: The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wordes of that <hi>Confession of Fayth,</hi> immediatly after the beginning of it, beeing these, <hi>Receaved, believed, defended by manie and sundrie notable Kirks and Realmes, but chieflie by the Kirke of Scotland, the Kings Majestie, and three estates of this Realme, as GOD'S eternall Trueth, and onlie groundof our Salvation,</hi> &amp;c. By which it is evident, that the <hi>Subscription</hi> to this <hi>Confession of Fayth,</hi> is to bee vrged in no other sense, than as it was then belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and receaved by the Kings Majestie, and the three Estates of this realme at that tyme in beeing; and it is well knowne, that at that time Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, Abbots, and Priors, made vp a third estate of this Realme, which gaue approbation to this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176900:11"/>
               <hi>Confession of Fayth:</hi> and therefore it is not to bee conceaved, that this third estate did then abjure <hi>Episcopacie,</hi> or that <hi>Episcopacie</hi> was at the first swearing of that <hi>Confession</hi> abolished. But say that at that tyme it was abolished by <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Generall Assemblie,</hi> yet was it not so by anie <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> nay, by manie <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> it was in force, because none of them was repealed; some whereof are annexed in the sheet immediatlie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter these reasons, which we pray the Reader care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie to peruse and ponder: and at the verie time of the taking of this <hi>Oath</hi> &amp; after, Bishops, whose names are well knowne, were in beeing. Now it is to bee hoped that in a Monarchie, or anie other well constituted republicke, that damnable Iesui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall position shall never take place, That which is once enacted by a Monarch &amp; his three estates in <hi>Parliament,</hi> shall ever bee helde repealed or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealable by anie Ecclesiasticall Nationall Synod.</p>
            <p>By all which it is evident, that the <hi>Explanation</hi> of that <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Councell</hi> so groundleslie vrged, can induce no man to imagine, that by the <hi>Confession of Fayth</hi> latelie sworne by his Majesties comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, <hi>Episcopall Government,</hi> which then did, and yet doeth stand established, by <hi>Acts</hi> of this Church and Kingdome, eyther was, or possiblie could bee abjured.</p>
            <p>And having nowe, good Reader, heard his Majesties mynde, in his <hi>Instructions</hi> to vs, our mynde in requyring, in his Majesties name, this <hi>Oath</hi> to bee taken, and these few <hi>Reasons</hi> of manie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176900:12"/>which doe evidentlie evince the in-consequence of that sense, which without anie showe of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, is put vpon it by those, who would goe on, in making men still belieue, that all which they doe or say, is grounded vpon <hi>Authoritie,</hi> though they themselues doe well knowe the contrarie: wee suppose, that all they who haue taken this <hi>Oath,</hi> wil rest satisfied, that they haue not abjured <hi>Episcopall Government;</hi> and, that they who shall take it, will take it in none other sense.</p>
            <p>Which tymelie <hi>Warning</hi> of ours, wee are the more willing to giue, because we are given to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that evē they who were wont to call the takers of this <hi>Oath,</hi> (notwithstanding of that <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation</hi> by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Councell</hi>) <hi>perjured and damned persons;</hi> and in their Pulpits, called the vrging of it, <hi>The depth of Satan,</hi> doe nowe meane to take it themselues, &amp; vrge others to take it in that sense which they make men belieue (though wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie) that <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Councell</hi> maketh advantageous to their endes.</p>
            <p>But we do, in his Majesties name, require, that none presume to take the sayd <hi>Oath,</hi> vnlesse they be required so to doe, by such as shall haue lawful authoritie from his Majesty, to administer it vnto them: being confident, that none eyther will, or can, take the sayd <hi>Oath,</hi> or anie other <hi>Oath,</hi> in anie sense, which may not consist with <hi>Episcopall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> having his Majesties sense; and so the sense of all lawfull <hi>Authoritie</hi> fullie explayned vnto them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HAMMILTOVN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="history">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:176900:12"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat <hi>Episcopall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction</hi> was in force by <hi>Actes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and no wayes abolished, nor sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, in the yeare 1580, nor at the tyme of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> within the Realme of <hi>Scotland,</hi> doeth evidentlie appeare by the <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> after mentioned.</p>
            <p>First; By the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1567, <hi>Cap.</hi> 2: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by at the tyme of <hi>Reformation,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi>'s authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was abolished, it is enacted by the sayde <hi>Act, That no Bishop, nor other Prelate in this Realme, vse anie jurisdiction in tyme comming, by the Bishop of Romes authoritie.</hi> And by the third <hi>Act</hi> of the same <hi>Parliament,</hi> whereby it is declared, <hi>That all Acts, not agreeing with GOD'S Word, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the Confession of Fayth approved by the Estates in that Parliament, to haue none effect nor strength in tyme to come.</hi> Whereby it is evident, that it was not the <hi>Reformers</hi> intention, to suppresse <hi>Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie;</hi> but that Bishops should not vse anie <hi>Iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> by the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> his authoritie. And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176900:13"/>seeing they did allowe <hi>Episcopacie</hi> to continue in the Church, that they did not esteeme the same contrarie to GOD'S Word, and <hi>Confession</hi> fore-sayd: as appeareth more clearlie by the sixth <hi>Act</hi> of the sayde <hi>Parliament;</hi> which is ratified in the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1579, <hi>Cap.</hi> 68; whereby it is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>That the ministers of the blessed Evangell of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS CHRIST, whom GOD of His mercie hath now raysed vp amongst vs, or heereafter shall rayse, agreeing with them that now liue in doctrine or administration of the Sacraments, and the people of this Realme that professe CHRIST, as Hee is now offered in His Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, and doe communicate with the holie Sacraments, as in the Reformed Churches of this Realme they are publicklie administrated, according to the Confession of the Fayth, to bee the onelie true and holie Church of IESVS CHRIST, within this Realme:</hi> without anie exception, by reason of <hi>Policie</hi> and <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline:</hi> declaring onelie such as eyther gayne-say the Word of the Evangell, according vnto the heads of the sayd <hi>Confession;</hi> or refuse the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the holie Sacraments, as they are nowe ministrated, to bee no members of the sayde Church, so long as they keep themselues so divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the societie of CHRIST'S Bodie. Whereby it is manifest, that it was not the sayde <hi>Reformers</hi> mynde, to exclude anie from that so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, by reason of <hi>Discipline;</hi> and, that they did not, at that tyme, innovate, or change anie thing in that <hi>Policie</hi> they found in the sayd Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:176900:13"/>
            <p> This is lykewyse evident, by the <hi>Oath</hi> to bee ministred to the King at his Coronation, by the eyght <hi>Act</hi> of the sayde <hi>Parliament,</hi> whereby hee is to sweare, <hi>to mayntayne the true Religion of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS CHRIST, the preaching of His holie Word, and due and right ministration of the Sacraments, now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved and preached within this Realme, and shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolish and gayn-stand all false Religion contrarie to the same;</hi> without swearing to anie <hi>Innovation</hi> of Policie, and Discipline of the Kirke.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, it doeth evidentlie appeare by these subsequent <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that by the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipall lawe of this Realme, Arch-bishops and Bishops, were not onlie allowed in the Church, but also had jurisdiction and authoritie, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne the same.</p>
            <p>First; By the 24 <hi>Act</hi> of the sayde <hi>Parliament:</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> whereby <hi>all civill priviledges graunted by our so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraygne Lord's Predecessours, to the Spirituall estate of this Realme, are ratified in all poyntes, after the forme and tenour hereof.</hi> And by the 35 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1571; whereby <hi>all and whatsoever Actes and Statutes made of before, by our soveraygne Lord, and his Predecessours, anent the Freedome and Libertie of the true Church of GOD, are ratified, and approved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the 46 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1572;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is declared, That Arch-bishops &amp; Bishops, haue the authoritie, &amp; are ordayned, to conveane and depriue, all inferiour persons, beeing Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, who shall not subscribe the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:176900:14"/>and giue their <hi>Oath,</hi> for acknowledging and recognoscing of our Soveraygne Lord, and his authoritie; and bring a <hi>Testimoniall</hi> in wryting therevpon, within a moneth after their admis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
            <p>By the 48 <hi>Act</hi> of the same <hi>Parliament;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is declared, That Arch-bishops and Bishops haue authoritie, at their <hi>Visitations,</hi> to designe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters Gleybes.</p>
            <p>By the 54 <hi>Act</hi> of the sayde <hi>Parliament;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Arch-bishops and Bishops, are authorized to nominate, and appoynt, at their <hi>Visitations,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in everie Parochin, for making and setting of the <hi>Taxation,</hi> for vpholding and reparing of Churches, and Church-yardes: and, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veane, trye, and censure, all persons, that shall be found to haue applyed to their owne vse, the Stones, Timber, or anie thing else, pertayning to Churches demolished.</p>
            <p>By the 55 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1573;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Arch-bishops and Bishops are authorized, to admonish persons married, in case of desertion, to adhere: and in case of disobedience, <hi>to direct charges, to the Minister of the Parochin, to proceede to the Sentence of Excommunication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the 63 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1578;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> whereby Bishops, (and where no Bishops are provided, the Commissioners of Diocesses) haue authoritie, to trye the Rents of Hospitalls, and call for the Foundations thereof.</p>
            <p>By the 69 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1579;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176900:14"/>the jurisdiction of the Church, is declared, <hi>to stand in preaching the Word of IESVS CHRIST, correction of Manners, and administration of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Sacramentes:</hi> And yet none other Authoritie nor Office-bearer allowed, and appoynted by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> than is allowed by the former <hi>Actes;</hi> but Arch-bishops and Bishops, intended to continue in their authoritie: as is cleare by these <hi>Actes</hi> following.</p>
            <p>First: By the 71 <hi>Act</hi> of the same <hi>Parliament;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> whereby persons returning from their Travels, are ordayned, within the space of twentie dayes after their returne, <hi>to passe to the Bishop, Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Commissioner of the Kirkes</hi> where they arriue and reside, and there offer to make and giue a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of their fayth: or then within fourtie days to remoue themselues foorth of the Realme.</p>
            <p>By the 99 <hi>Act</hi> af the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1581,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the foresaydes <hi>Acts</hi> are ratified and approved.</p>
            <p>By the 130 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1584,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is ordayned, that none of his Majesties Liedges and Subjects presume or take vpon hand, to impugne the dignitie and authoritie of the three Estates of this Kingdome, whereby the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and authoritie of the Kings Majesties su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> past all memorie of man, hath beene continued, <hi>or to seeke or procure the innovation or diminution of the power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the same three estates, or anie of them, in tyme comming, vnder the payne of Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the 131 <hi>Act</hi> of the same <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176900:15"/>all judgements and jurisdictions as well in spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall as temporall causes, in practise &amp; custome, during these twentie foure yeares by-past, not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by his Highnesse and three estates in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> are discharged: and whereby it is defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>That none of his Highnesse Subjectes of whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever qualitie, estate, or function they bee of, spirituall or temporall, presume, or take vpon hand, to convocate, conveane, or assemble themselues together, for holding of Councels, Conventions, or Assemblies, to treat, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult, or determinate in anie matter of estate, civill or Ecclesiasticall, (except in the ordinarie judgements) without his Majesties speciall commandement, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse licence had and obtayned to that effect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the 132 <hi>Act</hi> of the saide <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing Bishops, to try and judge Ministers guiltie of crymes meriting deprivation.</p>
            <p>By the 133 <hi>Act</hi> of the same <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Ministers exercing anie office beside their Calling, to bee tryed and adjudged culpable by <hi>their Ordinaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the 23 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1587.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all <hi>Acts</hi> made by his Highnesse, or his most noble Progenitors, anent the Kirke of GOD, and Religion presentlie professed, are ratified.</p>
            <p>By the 231 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1597.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, <hi>That our Soveraygne Lord, and his Highnesse Estates in</hi> Parliament, <hi>having speciall consideration of the great priviledges and immunities granted by his Highnesse Predecessours, to the holie Kirke within this Realme, and to the speciall persons exercing the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176900:15"/>offices, titles, and dignities of the Prelates within the same; Which persons haue ever represented one of the Estates of this Realme, in all conventions of the saydes Estates: and that the sayds priveledges and freedomes, have beene from tyme to tyme renued and conserved, in the same integritie wherein they were at anie tyme before. So that his Majestie acknowledging the same to bee fallen now vnder his Majesties most favourable protection; therefore his Majestie, with consent of the Estates, declareth, that the Kirke within this Realme, wherein the true Religion is professed, is the true and holie Church: And that such Ministers as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie at anie tyme shall please to provide to the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, Place, Title, and Dignitie of a Bishop, &amp;c. shall haue vote in</hi> Parliament, <hi>sicklyke and als freelie as anie other Ecclesiasticall Prelate had at anie tyme by-gone.</hi> And also declareth, that all Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickes vaking, or that shall vake, shall bee onelie disponed to actuall Preachers and ministers in the Church, or such as shall take vpon them to exerce the sayde Function.</p>
            <p>By the 2 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1606;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>the auncient and fundamentall Policie, consisting in the mayntenace of the three Estates of</hi> Parliament, <hi>beeing of late greatlie impared, and almost subverted, especiallie by the indirect abolishing of the estate of Bishops, by the Act of Annexation: albeit it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meaned by his Majestie, nor by his Estates, that the sayd Estate of Bishops, beeing a necessarie Estate of the</hi> Parliament, <hi>should anie wayes bee suppressed; yet by dismembring and abstracting from them of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176900:16"/>beeing brought in contempt and povertie, the sayde Estate of Bishops is restored, and redintegrate to their ancient and accustomed Honour, Dignities, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues, Priviledges, Lands, Teyndes, Rents, as the same was in the reformed Church, most amplie and free, at anie tyme before the</hi> Act <hi>of Annexation; rescinding and annulling all</hi> Actes <hi>of</hi> Parliament <hi>made in prejudice of the saides Bishops, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses, or anie of them, with all that hath followed, or may follow therevpon, to the effect they may peaceablie enjoye the Honours, Dignities, Priviledges, and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues, competent to them, or their estate, since the Reformation of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the 6 <hi>Act</hi> of the 20 <hi>Parliament;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> declaring, <hi>That Arch-Bishops and Bishops, are redintegrate to their former Authoritie, Dignitie, Prerogatiue, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and Iurisdictions, lawfullie pertayning and shall bee knowne to pertayne to them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By the 1 <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1617;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Arch-Bishops and Bishops, to bee elected by their Chapters, and no other wayes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated by the Rites and Order accustomed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176900:16"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES, By the grace of <hi>GOD,</hi> King of SCOTLAND, ENGLAND, FRANCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the <hi>FAYTH,</hi> To Our Lovits,</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>Herauldes, Pursevantes; Our Shyreffs in that part, conjunctlie, and severallie, speciallie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176900:17"/>constitute, Greeting. WHERE-AS, For the removing of the Disorders, which haue happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of late within this Kingdome; And, for set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a perfect Peace in the Church, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth there-of, WEE were pleased, to call and indict <hi>A FREE GENERALL AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEMBLIE,</hi> to bee holden at GLASGOW, the xxj day of <hi>November</hi> last; And for Our Subjects their better content and assurance, that they should bee freed of such thinges as by their <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Supplications</hi> given in to the Lordes of Our Privie Councell, they seemed to bee grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at, WEE, in some sort, prevented the <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblie,</hi> by discharging, by Our <hi>Proclamation,</hi> the <hi>Service-Booke, Booke</hi> of <hi>Canons,</hi> and <hi>High Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> freed and liberate all Our Subjectes, from practising of the fiue <hi>Articles,</hi> exeemed all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters at their entrie, from giving anie other <hi>Oath,</hi> than that which is contayned in the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament;</hi> Made all persons, both Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall and Civill, lyable to the Censure of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Generall Assemblie,</hi> or anie other <hi>Iudicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> competent, according to the nature of their Offence; Had declared all by-gone Disorders absolutelie forgotten, and forgiven: And last; For securing to all Posteritie, the Trueth, and Libertie of <hi>RELIGION,</hi> did command the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession</hi> of <hi>Fayth,</hi> and Band for mayntenance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and of Authoritie in defence of the fame, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrybed by Our deare Father, and his House<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176900:17"/>in ANNO 1580, to bee renewed, and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrybed agayne by Our Subjectes heere. And, albeit that this Our Gracious and Pious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, in stead of Obedience and Submission, rancountred open and publicke Opposition and Protestation agaynst the same; And that they continued their daylie and hourlie guarding and watching our Castle of <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> suffering no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to bee imported there-in, but at their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion: stopping and impeding anie importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ammunition, or other Necessaries what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so-ever, to anie of Our Houses within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Denying to Us their Soveraygne Lord, that Libertie and Freedome, which the meanest of them assumed to themselues, (an Act without precedent or example in the Christian World:) Lyke as they spared not, boldlie and openlie to continue their <hi>Conventions,</hi> and <hi>Councell-Tables,</hi> of Nobilitie, Gentrie, Ministers, and Burgesses, within the Citie of <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> Where, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the Lawes of the Kingdome, without warrand of Authoritie, they conveaned, assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and treated vpon Matters as well Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall as Civill; Sent their Injunctions and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions throughout the Countrey, to their subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Tables, and other vnder Ministers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by them for that effect: And, vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and pretext of Religion, exercising an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warranded Libertie, requyred obedience to their vnlawfull and illegall Directions, to the seene prejudice of Authoritie, and lawfull Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176900:18"/>Government. And not-with-standing it was evidentlie manifest, by the illegall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formall Course taken in the Election of the Commissioners for the <hi>Assemblie;</hi> whereof some of them were vnder the Censure of this Church; some vnder the Censure of the Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> some long since banished, for avowed teaching agaynst <hi>Monarchie:</hi> others of them suspended, and some admitted to the Ministerie, contrarie to the forme prescrybed by the Lawes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: others of them Rebells, and at the Horne: some of them confined, and all of them by <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Subscription,</hi> bound to the overthrowe of <hi>Episcopall Governament.</hi> And by this, and others their Under-hand-working, and private Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations; and Perswasions, had given just ground of Suspicion of their Partialitie; and so made themselues vnfit Iudges of what concerneth <hi>Episcopacie:</hi> And als, albeit it was sufficientlie cleared, by the peremptorie and illegall Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures of the Presbyteries, who at their owne hand, and by order of Lawe, and without due forme of Processe, thrust out Moderators law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie established, and placed others, whome they found moste inclynable to their turbulent Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moures, associate to themselues, for choosing of the Commissioners to the <hi>Assemblie,</hi> a Laicke Elder out of each Parioch; who beeing in moste places equall, if not moe in number than the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie, made choyse both of the Ministers who should bee Commissioners from the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176900:18"/>as also of a Laicke Elder, (which in tyme will proue to bee a dangerous Consequence, and import an heavie Burden to the Libertie of the Church, and Church-men) beeing more dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted therein, by the Warrandes of the foresayde pretended <hi>Tables,</hi> than by their owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes; as appeared by the severall Instructions sent from them, (farre contrarie to the Lawes of this Countrey, and lowable custome of this Church) some whereof were produced, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit by Our Commissioner, and publicklie read: One whereof directed to the Noble-men and Barons of each Presbyterie, doeth amongst ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other odde passages, require <hi>Diligence;</hi> lest (say they) by our owne <hi>Sillinesse</hi> and <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie,</hi> wee lose so fayre an occasion of our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie,</hi> both <hi>Christian</hi> and <hi>Civill.</hi> A strange phrase, to proceede from duetifull or loyall-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Subjectes! The other, to the Moderators of severall Presbyteries, vnder the Title of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Instructions,</hi> August 27, contayning, first, That these <hi>Private Instructions</hi> shall bee disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to none, but to Brethren well-affected to the <hi>Cause.</hi> 2. Order must be taken, that none be chosen Ruling-Elders, but <hi>Covenanters,</hi> and these well-affected to the <hi>Businesse.</hi> 3. That where the Minister is not well-affected, the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Elder bee chosen by the Commissioners of the Shyre, and spoken vnto particularlie for that effect. 4. That they bee carefull, that no Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell-men, Chapter-men, or a Minister, Iustice
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176900:19"/>of Peace bee chosen, although <hi>Covenanters,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they haue publicklie renounced or declared the vnlawfulnesse of their Places. 5. That the Ruling Elders, come from everie Church, in equall number with the Ministers. And if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister oppose, to put themselues in possession, notwithstanding of anie opposition. 6. That the Commissioner of the Shyre, cause conveane before him the Ruling Elder of everie Church, chosen before the day of the Election, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne them, vpon their Oath, That they giue voyce to none, but to those who are named al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie at the Meeting of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi> 7. That where there is a Noble-man in the boundes of the Presbyterie, hee bee chosen: and where there is none, there bee chosen a Baron, or one of the best Qualitie; and he only a <hi>Covenanter.</hi> 8. That the ablest man in everie Presbyterie bee provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to dispute, <hi>De potestate supremi Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in Ecclesiasticis praesertim inconvocandis Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis,</hi> &amp;c. Whereby it is moste evident, what Prelimitations, and indirect and partiall Courses, and dangerous Propositions, haue bene vsed in the Preparations and Elections to this pretended <hi>Assemblie.</hi> By which vnlawfull doinges, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho Wee had sufficient reason, to haue dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Meeting of the <hi>Assemblie,</hi> yet We plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed patientlie to attende the same: Still hoping, that when they were met together, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of Our Commissioner, and assistance of some well-affected Subjectes, who were to bee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176900:19"/>there, and by their owne seeing the reall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of what was promised by Our <hi>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they should haue beene moved to returne to the due obedience of Subjects. But when Wee perceaved, that ther turbulent Dispositions did increase, as was manifest by their reparing to the sayde pretended <hi>Assemblie,</hi> with great Troups and Bands of Men, all boden in feare of Warre, with Gunnes and Pistolls, contrarie to the Laws of this Kingdome, and in high contempt of Our <hi>Proclamation</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the xvj of <hi>November</hi> last. As also by their peremptorie refusing to the Assessoures authorized by US, (altho fewer in number than our dearest Father was in vse to haue) the power of Voting in this <hi>Assemblie,</hi> as formerlie they had done in all others: openlie averring, That Wee nor Our Commissioner had no farther power there, than the meanest Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner of their number: and by their partiall and vnjust refusing, and not suffering to bee read, the Reasons and Argumentes given in by the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and their Adherentes, to Our Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioner, why they ought not to proceede to the Election of a Moderator, neyther yet to the trying and admitting of the Commissioners, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were heard, tho in Our Name they were earnestly requested therevnto by Our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner. And not-with-standing that Our Commissioner, by Warrand from Us, gaue in vnder his hand, a sufficient Declaration of all that was contayned in Our late <hi>Proclamation:</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:176900:20"/>Bearing lykewyse Our Pleasure, of the Registra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the same in the Bookes of <hi>Assemblie,</hi> for full assurance of the Trueth and Libertie of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to all Our good Subjectes; as doeth clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie appeare by the Declaration it selfe, where-of the Tenour followeth: THE KING'S MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIE beeing informed, That manie of his good Subjectes haue apprehended, that by the introducing of the <hi>Service-Booke,</hi> and <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Canons,</hi> the inbringing of <hi>Superstition</hi> hath beene intended, hath beene graciouslie pleased to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge; Lyke as by These hee doeth discharge the <hi>Service Booke,</hi> and <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Canons,</hi> and the practise of them, and eyther of them; and annul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and rescindeth all <hi>Actes</hi> of <hi>Councell, Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,</hi> and other <hi>Actes</hi> and <hi>Deedes</hi> whatsoever that haue beene made, or published, for establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of them, or eyther of them; and declareth the same to bee null, and to haue no force, nor effect, in tyme comming. THE KING'S MAIESTIE, as hee conceaved for the ease and benefite of the Subjects, established the <hi>High Commission,</hi> that thereby <hi>Iustice</hi> might bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrate, and the faultes and erroures of such persons as are made lyable therevnto, taken or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with, and punished, with the more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie, and lesse trouble to the people: But fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his gracious intention therein to bee mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, hath beene pleased to discharge, Lyke as by These hee doeth discharge the same, and all <hi>Actes</hi> and <hi>Deedes</hi> whatsoever made for establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176900:20"/>thereof. AND, The King's Majestie beeing informed, That the vrging of the fiue <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> of <hi>Pearth Assemblie,</hi> hath bred Distraction in the <hi>CHVRCH</hi> and <hi>ESTATE,</hi> hath beene graciouslie pleased, to take the same to his Royall Consideration; and, for the Quyet and Peace of his Countrey, hath not onlie dispensed with the practise of the saydes <hi>Articles;</hi> But also dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all and whatsoever persons, from vrging the practise thereof, vpon eyther Laicke or Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall person whatsoever; And hath fred all his Subjectes, from all Censures and Paynes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ecclesiasticall or Secular, for not vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, practising, or obeying them, or anie of them, notwithstanding of anie thing contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the <hi>Actes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> or <hi>Generall As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblie,</hi> to the contrarie. AND, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie is farther contented, That the <hi>Assemblie</hi> take the same so farre to their consideration, as to represent it vnto the next <hi>Parliament;</hi> there to bee ratified, as the Estates shall bee found fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. AND, Because it hath beene preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, That <hi>Oathes</hi> haue beene administrated diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that which is set downe in the <hi>Actes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> his Majestie is pleased to declare by mee, That no other <hi>Oath</hi> shall be required of anie Minister at his Entrie, than that which is set downe in the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament.</hi> AND, That it may appeare howe carefull his Majestie is, that no <hi>Corruption,</hi> or <hi>Innovation,</hi> shall creepe into this Church, neyther yet anie <hi>Scandall, Vyce,</hi> or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176900:21"/>
               <hi>Fault,</hi> of anie person whatsoever, censurable or punishable by the <hi>Assemblie,</hi> goe long vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. HIS MAIESTIE is content to declare by mee, and assure all his good People, That <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assemblies</hi> shall bee kept so oft, and also oft, as the Essayres of this Church shall requyre. AND, That none of his good Subjectes may haue cause of <hi>Grievances,</hi> agaynst the Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges of the Prelates, HIS MAIESTIE is contented, That all and everie one of the present Bishops, and their Successoures, shall bee aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable, and accordinglie from tyme to tyme, censurable, according to their merites, by the <hi>Generall Assemblie.</hi> AND, To giue all his Majestie's good People full assurance, that hee never intended to admit anie <hi>Alteration,</hi> or <hi>Change,</hi> in the <hi>True Religion,</hi> professed within this Kingdome; AND, That they may bee truelie and fullie satisfied, of the Realitie of His Intentions, and integritie of the same, His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie hath beene pleased, to requyre and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund all his good Subjectes, to subscry be the <hi>Confession of Fayth,</hi> and <hi>Band for mayntenance there-of,</hi> and <hi>Of His Majestie's Person and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> formerlie signed by his deare Father, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1580; And nowe also requyreth all these of this present <hi>Assemblie,</hi> to subscrybe the same. AND, It is his Majesties will, That this bee insert and registrate in the Books of <hi>Assemblie,</hi> as a <hi>Testimoniall</hi> to <hi>Posteritie,</hi> not onelie of the sinceritie of his Intentions to the sayd <hi>True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:176900:21"/>but also of His Resolution, to mayntayne and defende the same, and His Subjectes, in the Profession there-of. Which Declaration was by Our speciall Commaund and Direction given in, and subscrybed by Our Commissioner, vpon Protestation made by him, That his assenting to the registrating heere-of, should bee no Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the lawfulnesse of this <hi>Assemblie,</hi> nor of anie of the Actes of Deedes done or to bee done therein. And finding them in lyke sort, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to besatisfied therewith, and that nothing else was able to giue them content, except at their owne pleasure they were permitted to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe all <hi>Episcopall Governament</hi> in the Church, and thereby to abrogate Our publicke Lawes standing in vigour, by the space of manie yeares by-gone, and to alter the fundamentall Governa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdome, in taking away one of three Estates, contrarie expresse <hi>Actes</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> And lest the continuance of their mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, might haue produced other the lyke dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Actes</hi> so derogatorie to Royall <hi>Authoritie;</hi> Wee were forced for preveaning thereof, and for the causes and reasons aboue mentioned, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse others importing true Monarchicall <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament,</hi> to dissolue and breake vp the sayde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Assemblie,</hi> and to discharge them of all far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meeting, treating, or concluding of anie thing therein: And yet in that calme and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able way, as Our Commissioner before his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving desired their pretended Moderator for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176900:22"/>that tyme, to haue sayde Prayer, and so conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that dayes <hi>Session;</hi> that so they might haue had tyme to thinke vpon the just reasons of his refusing, to assist or bee anie longer present at the sayde pretended <hi>Assemblie;</hi> and of the causes moving Us to the dissolving thereof. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding his earnest vrging the same, and being willing to returne the next Morne to heare their Answere, in place of all other satisfaction to his so reasonable and moderate desires, was refused, and met with a <hi>Protestation,</hi> of an high and extraordinarie strayne: Thereby presuming to sute and call our Counsell in question, for their duetifull assistance, and obedience vnto Us, and Our Commissioner. And finding their disobedience thus to increasse, Wee were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strayned to discharge them anewe agayne the next daye thereafter, by publicke <hi>Proclamation,</hi> vnder the Payne of Treason. And albeit that their continuance is such, as hath not beene heard in former tymes, yet they shall never moue Us, to alter the least poynt or <hi>Article</hi> of what Wee haue alreadie declared by <hi>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>Declaration</hi> vnder Our Commissioner's hand: All which was publicklie read, and by our Commissioner requyred to bee insert and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrated in the Bookes of <hi>Assemblie,</hi> therein to remayne as a <hi>Testimonie</hi> to Posteritie; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of the sinceritie of Our Intentions to the true <hi>Religion;</hi> but also of Our Resolution, to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and defende the same, and Our Subjectes,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176900:22"/>in the Profession thereof. AND perceaving lykewyse, That in contempt of OUR PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLAMATION at <hi>GLASGOW,</hi> the xxix of NOVEMBER last, they goe still on, to conveane, meete, and to make illegall and vnwarrandable <hi>Actes,</hi> WEE haue conceaved it fitting, to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne all Our good Subjectes, of the Daunger that they may incurre, by beeing insnared by these their vnlawfull Procedures: And, to this purpose, doe not onelie liberate and free them, from all obedience to anie of the pretended <hi>Actes</hi> made, or to bee made, at the sayde pretended <hi>Assemblie,</hi> or Committees direct therefrae: but also doe free them from all <hi>Payne</hi> and <hi>Censure</hi> which the sayde pretended <hi>Assemblie</hi> shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict vpon them, or anie of them: AND, THEREFORE, Doe discharge, and prohibite, all Our Subjectes, That they, nor none of them, acknowledge, or giue obedience, to anie preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Actes,</hi> or <hi>Constitutions,</hi> made, or to bee made, at the sayde pretended <hi>Meetinges,</hi> vnder all highest <hi>Paynes.</hi> AND, WEE commaund, charge, and inhibite, all Presbyteries, Sessions of Churches, and Ministers, within this Realme, That none of them presume, nor take vpon hand, privatelie, nor publicklie, in their <hi>Sessions</hi> and <hi>Meetinges,</hi> nor in their <hi>Conferences, Sermones,</hi> nor none other manner of waye, to authorize, approue, justifie, or allowe, the sayde vnlawfull <hi>Meeting,</hi> or <hi>Assemblie,</hi> at <hi>GLASGOW,</hi> nor yet to make anie <hi>Act</hi> therevpon, nor to doe any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176900:23"/>other thing, private, or publicke, which may seeme to countenance the sayde vnlawfull <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblie,</hi> vnder the <hi>Payne</hi> to bee holden, repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and esteemed, and persued, as guiltie of that vnlawfull <hi>Meeting,</hi> and to bee punished for the same, with all Rigour. AND SUCH-LYKE, WEE commaund all and sundrie Noble-men, Barrons, Gentle-men, Magistrates, and all others Our Liedges, who shall happen to bee present, and heare anie Ministers, eyther in publicke or private <hi>Conferences</hi> and <hi>Speaches,</hi> or in their <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones,</hi> to approue, and allowe, the sayde vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Assemblie,</hi> rayle, or vtter anie speaches agaynst Our Royall Command ementes, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinges of Us, or our Counsell, for punishing or supperessing such Enormities; That they make relation, and report thereof, vnto Our Counsell, and furnish probation; to the effect the same may bee accordinglie punished; as they will aunswere to US therevpon: Certifying them, who shall heare, and conceale the sayde speaches, that they shall bee esteemed, as Allowers of the same, and shall accordinglie bee taken order with, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished therefore, without favour. AND, To this effect, WEE lykewyse straytlie charge, and commaund, all Iudges whatsoever within this Realme, Clerks, and Wryters, not to graunt or passe anie Bill, Summonds, or Letters, or anie other Execution whatsoever, vpon anie <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Deed</hi> proceeding from the sayde pretended <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblie;</hi> AND all Keepers of the <hi>SIGNET,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:176900:23"/>from signetting thereof, &amp; that vnder all highest <hi>Paynes.</hi> AND, Because Wee gaue Order and Commaund, to Our Commissioner, to make open <hi>Proclamation,</hi> not onlie of Our Sense, but even of the true meaning of the <hi>Confession</hi> of <hi>Fayth,</hi> in ANNO 1580; by which it may clearlie appeare, That as Wee never intended thereby to exclude <hi>EPISCOPACIE;</hi> So by no right construction can it bee other wayes interpreted; as is more than evident by the Reasons contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the sayde <hi>Declaration,</hi> and manie moe, which for brevitie (the thing in it selfe beeing so cleare) are omitted. HEREFORE, WEE doe not onelie prohibite, and discharge, all Our Subjectes, from subscrybing anie <hi>Band,</hi> or giving anie <hi>Writ, Subscription,</hi> or <hi>Oath,</hi> to or vpon anie <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Deed,</hi> that proceedeth from the sayde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Assemblie:</hi> But also doe requyre them, Not to subscrybe nor sweare the sayd <hi>Confession,</hi> in no other sense, than which is contayned in the sayd <hi>Declaration,</hi> manifested and emitted by Our Commissioner, vnder all highest <hi>Paynes.</hi> AND, That none of Our good Subjectes, who in their duetie and bound obedience to US, shall refuse to acknowledge the sayd pretended <hi>Assemblie,</hi> or anie of the pretended <hi>Actes, Constitutions, Warrandes,</hi> or <hi>Directions,</hi> proceeding therefrae, may haue just ground of feare of danger or harme by doing hereof, WEE doe by These promise, AND, UPON THE WORD OF A KING, Obliedge Our Selues, By all the Royall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176900:24"/>Authoritie and Power wherewith GOD hath endewed US, To protect and defend them, and everie one of them, in their Persons, Fortunes, and Goods, agaynst all and whatsoever person or persons, who shall dare or presume, to call in question, trouble, or anie wayes molest them, or anie of them, therefore. AND,</p>
            <p>OUR WILL IS, And WEE commaund, and charge, That incontinent, these Our Letter seene, yee passe, and make publication heereof, by open Proclamation, at the Mercat Crosse of <hi>EDINBVRGH,</hi> and others places needfull; Where-through none pretend igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the same. Given from Our Court, at <hi>WHYTE-HALL,</hi> the viij day of <hi>December,</hi> and of Our Reygne the fourteenth yeare, 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>